2.1 Enterprise Environmental Factors
Enterprise Environmental Factors,
EEFs, refer to conditions not under the
control of the project team that
influence, constrain or direct the
project.
These conditions can be internal and or
external to the organization.
Enterprise environmental factors are
considered as inputs to many project
management processes, specifically for
most planning processes.
These factors may enhance our constrained
project management options.
In addition, these factors may have a
positive or negative
influence on the outcome.
That's from PIMBOC guide, page 38.
So what are these environmental factors
then?
There are many different types of
enterprise environmental factors,
but they can be divided into
two distinct groups, those that
are external to the organization
and those that are internal.
I like to think of enterprise environmental
environmental factors this way.
Imagine you and your project team are
traveling to another
country on a cruise ship.
This is where you're managing your
project.
The ship represents the organizational
enterprise environmental factors internal.
So the ones internal to the ship would be
resource availability, e.g.
the vision, mission, values, belief of the
shipping company, the rules on board the
ship, the expected behaviour of the crew
and passengers, the Code of Ethics and
Rule of Law, the leadership
of the captain, as well as
the hierarchy and authority
relationships of crew members.
Geographical distribution of facilities
and resources, e.g., there would be a
floor plan of a ship showing the
facilities on each deck and you would have
information about your cabins and where to
eat, for example.
Infrastructure, e.g., there
would be details of what
equipment is available for
you to use on board the ship.
For example, computers, the gym equipment.
There would be resource availability,
e.g., you would have a list of staff
available to help you, and there would be
a shop for purchasing items.
Employee capability.
There would be a list of services that can
be provided at the
times that are available.
They would include medical, a gym
instructor, religious services,
financial services, dance instruction and
so on.
These are the enterprise environmental
factors internal to the cruise liner.
But what about the organization?
One, enterprise environmental factors
internal to an organization.
These would include organizational
culture, structure and governance,
as before, e.g., vision, values,
belief, cultural norms, leadership style,
hierarchy and authority relationships,
organizational style,
ethics and code of conduct.
Then we had geographic distribution of
facilities and resources, easy factory
resources, virtual teams, shared systems,
cloud computing.
There's the infrastructure.
Examples include existing
facilities, equipment,
organizational telecommunication
channels, information
technology hardware,
availability and capacity.
Information technology software examples
include scheduling software tools,
configuration management
systems, web interfaces to other
online automated systems
and work authorization systems.
Resource availability examples include
contract and purchasing constraints,
approved providers and subcontractors in
collaboration agreements.
And then employee capability.
Examples include existing
human resource expertise,
skills, competencies
and specialist knowledge.
Let's go to our cruise
liner and consider the
enterprise environmental
factors external to the ship.
There's the marketplace conditions,
e.g.
the other competitor shipping companies
that you could have traveled with,
the reputation of the
shipping company that
you chose, the name
and low of the company.
Social and cultural influences and issues,
e.g.
political climate, codes of
conduct, ethics and perceptions
of the countries that
you're travelling through.
Legal restrictions, for example,
country or local laws or regulations.
For example, you're not allowed to consume
alcohol in some countries and in others,
such as Australia, there are many types of
food that you're not
allowed to bring ashore.
Commercial databases e.g.
tables of average ticket prices and
expected facilities, as well as published
data on risk studies, safety reputation of
the various ocean liners, etc.
Academic research, e.g.
online forums and
review sites that rate and
compare shipping
companies and their offerings.
Next is government or industry standards,
e.g.
health and safety laws, employment laws,
such as anti-discrimination, minimum wage,
certifications for crew and equipment,
sea worthness, certification for the ship,
laws relating to the storage, preparation
and serving at food.
And then financial considerations,
e.g.
currency exchange rates, interest rates,
inflation rates, tariffs
and geographic location.
Then the physical environment elements,
e.g.
working conditions, weather and
constraints.
Okay, so these are the
enterprise environmental
factors external to our cruise line.
but how would we apply those to an
organisation?
So enterprise and
environmental factors external
to the organisation,
marketplace conditions, e.g.
competitors, brand share, recognition and
trademarks.
Social and cultural influences and issues,
e.g.
political climate, codes of conduct,
ethics and perceptions.
Then legal restrictions.
Examples include country or local laws and
regulations related to security,
data protection, business conduct,
employment and procurement.
Commercial databases, e.g.
Benchmarking results,
standardized cost-estimating
data, industry risk
information, and risk databases.
Academic research, e.g.
industry studies,
publications and benchmarking
results, and government
or industry standards.
Examples include regulatory agency and
standards related to products,
production, environment, quality and
workmanship.
Financial considerations, e.g.
currency, exchange rates, interest rates,
inflation rates, tariff
and geographic location.
Physical environment elements would be
working conditions, weather and constraints.
The same as on boardership.
That brings us to the end of enterprise
environmental factors.
I hope by analogy with the cruise ladder
helps you find your sea legs.
Next lesson is 2.2, organizational
process.
Please read the corresponding chapter in
the pinball guide before
watching the video.